Guide to the Rice University memorabilia collection, 1912-2022 UA 225
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University memorabilia collection
1912-2022
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University.
UA 225
191 Linear Feet 178 boxes plus oversize items
This collection contains a wide variety of realia from Rice University's history, including a variety of jewelry pieces, clothing, athletics-related materials, and various other objects.
Biographical / Historical
Rice University was founded in 1891 and opened in 1912. The memorabilia in this collection reflects many aspects of the university's history, from social life, academic life, athletics, administration, architectural elements, symbols such as the seal and shield.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains a wide variety of realia from Rice University's history, including a variety of jewelry pieces, clothing, athletics-related materials, and various other objects.
Access Restrictions
This material is available for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Acquisition Information
The items in this collection were transferred from other university departments or donated by Rice alumni throughout the years.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges; Sports
Document Types
posters; Collectibles
- Series I: Memorabilia, boxed
  - Original campus china (Box 1-4)
  - Sub-series A: Rice residential college china
    - Lovett & Wiess (Box 5)
    - Hanszen & Jones (Box 6)
    - Brown & Will Rice (Box 7)
    - Sid Richardson (Box 8)
    - Martel & Baker (Box 9)
  - William Marsh Rice Society and Rice Institute commemorative plates (Box 10)
  - Lovett Hall commemorative plates (Box 11)
  - Semi-Centennial commemorative plates [sent to W.M. Standish from C.N. Coleman; W.C. Williams nee D. Lottman] (Box 12)
  - Sub-series B: Wedgwood commemorative plates
    - Campus building scenes with floral border (1 complete set of 4, 1 Lovett, 3 Chemistry) (Box 13)
    - Campus building scenes with ribbed border (complete set of 4) (Box 14-17)
    - Campus building scenes with ribbed border (2 Campanile, 1 Chemistry) (Box 18)
  - Mugs & glasses, plastic water bottles (Box 19)
  - White ceramic steins with Rice seal (4); "Mug at the Pub" plastic stein (Box 20)
  - MOB barley beer poster with unopened bottle; 11 Rice Seal glasses (Box 21)
  - Stainless steel travel mugs; plastic, ceramic coffee mugs; glass jar with lid (Box 22)
  - Frosted Rice Institute glasses (Box 23)
  - William McVey wooden & metal owl sculptures; '28 R shield (Box 24)
  - Faux marble oval plaque with stylized owl for class of '52 (Box 25)
  - Rice Owlopoly game (Box 26)
  - Carved Rice owl toilet seat (Box 27)
  - Owls: plush, bronze, painted on marble, soap (Box 28)
  - Carved owl bookends 1916 (Box 29)
  - Pottery owl bookends (Box 30)
  - Aluminum Rice owl tray (Box 31)
  - "Fear the Owl" sculpture (Box 32)
  - Rice Alumni Association giveaways (Box 33)
  - Rice Alumni Association Lego model kit of Lovett Hall (3) & Lego blue owl; Rice University domino set (Box 34)
  - Distinguished Rice alumnus award 2010 to James Mischka (Box 35)
  - Rice class rings and student IDs (Box 36)
  - Rally Club ceramic steins: Ed '51, Billy '57 (4), Jack '49 (2) (Box 37)
  - Edwin Ford Beckenbach '28 items donated by Glenda Howell Baker '60 (Box 38)
  - Jewelry, watches, fobs (Box 39)
  - Humble Oil latex Rice owl figures (Box 40)
  - Belts & buckles, red sealing wax/seal (Box 41)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes buckle donated by Ed Jennings, Class of 1948
  - Tau Beta Pi key; campanile marble column sample; helium liguifier dedication plaque (Box 42)
  - 1930, 1933, 1938 class items donated by G.B. Kitchel (Box 43)
  - Commemorative spoons, kaleidoscope, perfume bottle... (Box 44)
  - Rice pins (Box 45)
  - Medals & medallions (Box 46-47)
  - Stedman framed b&w original illustrations for 1928 Campanile (Box 48-49)
  - Painting/collage of Rice campus scenes & Lovett Hall by Bill Condon (Box 50)
  - Slide rule, rock football player, pencil holders, new steel for rebuilt entrance gate, engineering set (Box 51)
  - Ashtrays with Rice seal; music boxes (Box 52)
  - Bronze replicas of William Marsh Rice statue (Box 53)
  - Paperweights (Box 54)
  - Pewter engraved plate from 1992 Commencement speaker Helmut Schmidt (Box 55)
  - Plaques (2) from Hispanic Engineering HENAAC (Box 56)
  - E.D. Butcher (fist Chairman Rice Univ. Fund Council) gavel 1971-72; Rice green glass box (Box 57)
  - Baker Institute commemorative plates (Box 58)
  - Semi-Centennial plaques by Texas National Bank (Box 59)
  - George R. Brown Hall groundbreaking plaques (3) 1989; wave brick (Box 60)
  - William Marsh Rice Society blue Block vases (2); 1993 Gillis 'train' invitation (Box 61)
  - Rice service award samples (Box 62)
  - Rolm phones, Gilbane hardhats (Box 63)
  - Tudor Fieldhouse crystal thank-you to major donors (Box 64)
  - Tudor Fieldhouse & Gibbs Recreation Center giveaways; RSA Hedge Hoppers; 2001 DeLange Conference speakers gift; gold ping pong balls; Graduate Apts. financing program commemorative (Box 65)
  - Buckyballs & 1996 Nobel Prize commemorative items (Box 66)
  - Rice Art Car parade material (Box 67)
  - Friends of Fondren giveaways (Box 68)
  - Fondren Library Meritorious Design Award, 1950; Howard Keck Hall ceremonial key, 2000; Fondren Library physical distancing (Covid-19) floor sticker (Box 69)
  - AIDS memorial quilt names project panels 2000s (Box 70)
  - Rice owl blanket, bright blue fringed (Box 71)
  - Owl quilt (Box 72)
  - "R" blanket-Wash Underwood '27 (Box 73)
  - "R" blanket new version for 1941 Bob Quin Award to J.M. "Dick" Morris (Box 74)
  - "R" blankets (2) appliqued with Autry label, custom-made gray binding (Box 75)
  - "R" blanket with owl applique, Allie May Autry ca.1921 (Box 76)
  - Rice seal blanket ca.1921 (Box 77)
  - "R" blankets (2) original; "R" blanket 1941 Allie May Autry Kelley & Mike Kelley (Box 78)
  - Rice Memorial Center floor mat (Box 79)
  - Rice Institute seal rug ca.1961 (Box 80)
  - Rice buildings original door hardware (Box 81)
  - Plaster model of Sophocles for Administration Bldg. (Lovett Hall) capital; reserve presidential medal (Box 82)
  - Muleshoe and horseshoe excavated in 2012 between RMC and Brochstein Pavilion; Jacob Boehler time capsule (Box 83)
    1911 - Prince Albert tobacco can containing a piece of wood with the name Jacob Boehler. Found in 2021 during the Mech Lab renovation.
  - Wedge and trowel used in setting cornerstone of Rice Institute Administration Bldg. 1911 (Box 84)
  - Wiess residential President's house related items (Box 85)
  - Rice original buildings lighting fixtures (Box 86-87)
  - Class/commencement printed materials (Box 88-89)
  - Tubes: woodson (empty); blue used for Rice diplomas; ceremonial wooden maces (3) (Box 90)
  - Invitations and programs in wooden tubes to opening of Rice Institute 1912 (Box 91)
  - Materials Lab bellows (Box 92)
  - Rice Institute Library book identifier cutter (Box 93)
  - Rice Institute embosser (Box 94)
  - President E.O. Lovett office desk contents (Box 95)
    General
    This box includes Dr. Lovett's glasses and the certificate from Dr. Shannon Walker's space flight in 2021 with the glasses.
  - Bursar office sign (Box 96)
  - Mechanical Laboratory ammeter (Box 97)
  - Lovett Hall building core samples (Box 98)
  - Proofs for Lovett Hall flags (2) (Box 99)
  - Rice banners (Box 100-101)
  - Rice Institute banner ca.1916 (Box 102)
  - Dept. of Architecture banner (Box 103)
  - Capital Campaign banner 2008/09 (Box 104)
  - Semi-Centennial banner and Rice Institute pennant (Box 105)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Pennant donated by Nancy Henry in summer of 2019.
  - Dalai Lama blessed scarves 2007; Dalai Lama event VIP passes 2005 (Box 106)
  - Bandanas: Martel, Unconventional Wisdom, Rice (Box 107)
  - Mask, 2021 (Box 107)
    Sally Ride Festival mask. Event organized by Pat Rieff. 1st student event on campus after 2020-03 shutdown. Donated by Emma Kolah
  - Rice flag flown aboard STS-109, Columbia 2002 and stickers from SIDE experiments that flew on Apollo 12, 13, 14, and 15. (Box 108)
    Stickers donated by Kimbol Soques in the summer of 2019.
  - Student dances; student papers (Box 109-111)
  - Electrical Engineering 543 laboratory reports 1962-63 (Box 112)
  - Molecular models (Box 113)
  - Residential college seals (Box 114)
  - Rice shield patches, Rice colors, McCants "Story of Owl Eyes & coin" (Box 115)
  - Rice seals and shields (Box 116)
  - Rice shields (Box 117)
  - Rice seals and shields framed (Box 118)
  - Rice seal/shield banner (rod in vault corner) (Box 119)
  - Glass disks for Rice Memorial Center glass curtain (Box 120)
  - Rice buildings room plaques (Box 121)
  - Rice Memorial Center room plaques (Box 122)
  - Bricks from various campus sites, buildings (Box 123)
  - E.O. Lovett statue bronze maquette in wooden presentation box from sculptor to Pres. Gillis (Box 124)
  - Cheerleading pompoms and Rice giveaways (Box 125)
  - Rice giveaways (Box 126)
  - Rice giveaways (Box 26A)
  - Rice pennants, "R" letters, NROTC items (Box 127)
    Includes a pennant with an attached ticket stub donated by Kenneth Simmons.
  - Small blankets, pennants, towels, soccer scarf (Box 128)
  - Rice basketball memorabilia (Box 129)
  - Rice baseball bobbleheads, balls, cards (Box 130)
  - Brick from Cameron Field (baseball) last game played there 5-1-1999 (Box 131)
  - Reckling Park dedication 2000; Wayne Graham bobblehead & signed baseball (Box 132)
  - Reckling Park opening day 2000; signed baseballs; miniature Louisville slugger (Box 133)
  - Rice baseball shirts, flag, scarf (Box 134)
  - Rice World Series 2003 memorabilia (Box 135)
  - Rice World Series 2003 national championship (Box 136)
    - President Malcolm Gillis's Rice Athletic Championship Rings (Box 136)
      1996 SWC Champions Forever ring 1997 WAC Champions NCAA College World Series ring 2003 NCAA World Series Championship ring 1994 SWC Football Champions ring
  - Rice plush baseball player (Box 137)
  - Rice youth baseball bat & ball (Box 138)
  - Rice football purse, megaphone, MOB kazoo, coin with football schedule (Box 139)
  - Football themed decorations, pinwheels, owls (Box 140)
  - Rice football cards, press pass, Oil Bowl ticket (Box 141)
  - Rice football helmet signed (Box 142)
  - 1961 Sugar Bowl portrait in sugar of Ken Simmons, guard (Box 143)
  - 1961 Sugar Bowl portrait in sugar of Bill Simmons, end (Box 144)
  - Rice stadium folding seat (Box 145)
  - Rice football player bobblehead, Willis Wilson Bobblehead (Box 146)
  - Rice football player soft sculpture; 1953 Cotton Bowl items (Box 147)
  - Hawaii Bowl 2014 memorabilia (Box 148)
  - Calendars with Rice football program covers 2008-16; 2012 VIP parking passes; turf samples and supporting materials, piece of Media Center Darkroom flooring with etching made by John Gladu (Box 149)
  - R&L Carriers 2006 New Orleans Bowl memorablia (Box 150)
  - Orange Bowl 1947 memorabilia (Box 151)
  - Rice football games giveaways; A&M cadet voodoo doll; Ceramic owl football decanter by McCormick,1972 (Box 152)
  - SMU v. Rice silver Revere bowl 10-17-1950 (Box 153)
  - Cotton Bowl banner 1950 Rice v. UNC (Box 154)
  - Cotton Bowl Classic blanket (Box 155)
  - Cotton Bowl Classic blanket 1954 (Box 156)
  - Rice football jersey # 43 Calhoun; Rice shirt (Box 157)
  - Footballs (some signed by players/coaches) (Box 158-161)
  - Trophies: athletics & debate (Box 162-163)
  - Trophies: football championships 1934, 1937 (Box 164)
  - Award plaque: Chief of Engineers ROTC summer camp Fort Leonard Wood 1959 (Box 165)
  - Award plaques: athletic & debate; labels removed from broken trophies 1955-1978 (Box 166)
  - Award plaque: Lester Curran Award to Charles S. Matthews 1975 (Box 167)
  - Trophies: Rugby; South Central Collegiate Cycling Conference; cricket, rowing regatta labels (Box 168)
  - Trophies (Box 169)
  - Trophies; tennis & track/field medals (Box 170)
  - NCAA tennis championship racket-Frank Guernsey (Box 171)
  - Athenian drachma coin [owl] (Box 172)
  - Rice MOB blanket, 1986 (Box 173)
    Biographical / Historical
    The donor describes blankets like this one being awarded to seniors who had been in the Marching Owl Band (MOB) for four years.
    Anonymous Donor through Greg Marshall in August of 2019.
  - Jesse H. Jones Graduate School of Management Construction Hat, n.d. (Box 174)
    Donated by Dean Whitaker in the summer of 2019.
  - Watercolor/Ink drawing of the first art studio at Rice by Peter Sartorius, class of 68, 1966 (Box 175)
  - Framed owl pictures (2) (Box 176)
  - Athletic sweaters (Box 177)
    Lew Harpold "R" cardigan, D. Dean "R" sweater
  - 2022 Conference USA Champions Volleyball t-shirt (Box 178)
  - 60th anniversary of the JFK moonshot speech football jersey (Box 178)
- Series II: Memorabilia, oversize and unboxed
  - Wischmeyer plaster owl (Oversize on top of card catalog WRC 160)
  - Stuffed barn owl presented to Rice Institute by George Washington University's Rouser's Club Nov. 2, 1935 (Oversize WRC 160C)
  - Stuffed owl from campus bookstore (Oversize WRC 160B)
  - Stuffed owl from RMC trophy case (Oversize WRC 160A)
  - Franklin Mint porcelain owl from Alumni Association (Oversize WRC 160)
  - Buckyball model (Oversize vault aisle 2)
  - Rice cheerleading megaphones (Oversize vault aisle 2)
  - Trophy: Southwest Athletic Conference Champions (tie) basketball 1935 (Oversize vault top shelf range 2)
  - Eddie Wojecki, trainer 1946-67, bronze plaque (Oversize vault bottom shelf range 2)
  - Trophy: Southwest Conference Cross Country 1926 (Oversize vault top shelf range 2)
  - Trophy: Bayou Bucket Shootout, UH v. Rice, first place net (Oversize vault second shelf range 2)
  - Trophy: SWC Relay Champions 1926 (Oversize top of control folder file cabinet)
  - Trophy: SWC Track Champions 1922 (Oversize top of control folder file cabinet)
  - Shovels & spades for groundbreaking (Oversize vault back corner)
  - Cohen House sundial original directional arrows (Oversize vault back corner)
  - Tin tube (empty) "Rice Land and Lumber Company" (Oversize vault back corner)
  - Rice mascot owl house model with newsclip (Oversize vault back range 4 top shelf)
  - Track cross bar from bamboo pole (see memorabilia corresp.) (Oversize Annex top shelf inside door)
  - Rocket with base SAMMY 1964-65 (Oversize Annex)
  - Maquette of Dr. Edgar Odell Lovett statue on Rice University camps, presented in custom padded box with Rice seal on top (Oversize vault back corner)
    Accession # 2020.UA053
- Series III: Memorabilia in upright picture cases
  - Vault
    - Frank C. Dill artwork: Sallyport view of Willy's statue for Pres. Hackerman original rendering; Trinity Episcopal Church pen & ink drawing given to W.W.Watkin by Ray & Rosemary Watkin; "Main Street, Houston, Texas" (Bin Slot 1)
    - Framed studio photo of clay model for Willy's statue by John Angel; E.O. Lovett's copy 1930; Pershing Day poster (Bin Slot 2)
    - Engraving plates (2); Baker College coat of arms (framed); small American flag and patch flown aboard Space Shuttle Columbia, April 1981 (Bin Slot 3)
    - Poster of King Hill & Frank Ryan undated b&w comic strip look; W.W. Watkin oil portrait signed by Lila Shelby '59 (Bin Slot 4)
    - John Clark Tidden "original painting from which illustrations for Classes 1916 Campanile was reproduced (framed) given by Alva Kalb Dumas in memory of E.F. Kalb '15; Hand drawn rendering of Lovett Hall from Assoc. of Rice Alumni to John T. McCants Nov. 13, 1953 (Bin Slot 5)
    - "Fightin' Owls" framed basketball poster (Bin Slot 6)
    - Louis Pasteur framed lithograph to Pres. Lovett from the French Educational Mission 1918-19; "Thank you for supporting Rice athletics" blue & white sign; framed 1918 Rice pennant with handwritten permission for E.H. Dyer & A.W. Mount to study late during SATC days of 1918 (Bin Slot 7)
    - Framed CPA certificate for Russ Pitman 7-26-1959; plaque for Tau Beta Phi Texas Gamma Chapter 64th convention 10-11-1969; Woodson Research Center plastic laminate sign (Bin Slot 8)
    - William McVey terracotta plaque "Freshman Flogging" from Hanszen first commons 1956-57 (Bin Slot 9)
    - Borden Freshman Prize for highest average grade plaque 1956-70 (Bin Slot 10)
    - Senior walking cane engraved EFK (Ervin Kalb '16) framed and mounted; 1993 senior cane Tom Karsten (Bin Slot 11)
    - Woodson Research Center brass plaque (Bin Slot 12)
    - Reckling Park groundbreaking framed photo 5-1-1999; Rice 1912-2012 Engaging the World Rice Centennial mounted poster (Bin Slot 13)
    - Pitman Tower framed watercolor rendering; Stockton Axson framed chalk portrait by McKenna 1932 (Bin Slot 14)
    - empty (Bin Slot 15)
    - Framed color photo of Charles S. Matthews -Assoc. of Rice Alumni for achievement in Engineering 5-7-1994; Humble Oil & Ref. Co. William Rice fee well no. 1, 236 acres+- metal sign (Bin Slot 16)
    - U@C60 framed image of Buckministerfullerene Rice Quantum Institute; framed color photo of George Rupp, Malcolm Gillis, David Leebron, Norman Hackerman at Rice University 10-2-2004 (Bin Slot 17)
    - Framed b&w print of Lovett Hall by Charles Capps; framed Rice University seal (Bin Slot 18)
    - Nobel Prize Award to Richard Smalley & Robert Curl 10-9-1996, framed with proclamations for each with medal replica (Bin Slot 19)
    - Hanszen Relocation Dedication Plaque, 1976-04-10 (Bin Slot 19)
    - Joyce Pounda Hardy plaque plate, 1992 (Bin Slot 19)
    - Rice Victory plaque, 1945-07 (Bin Slot 19)
      Plaque reads: Rice Victory Built for U.S. Maritime Commission, Hull NO. V-797, by California Shipbuilding Corporation, Los Angeles, California, July 1945
    - Dr. Ted Lewis photo 90th birthday greeting 5-6-2010; hand-scribed framed vellum pages (2) to E.O. Lovett by Board of Trustees 5-12-1946 (Bin Slot 20)
    - Hand-scribed framed vellum pages (2) to E.O. Lovett by Board of Trustees 5-12-1946 (Bin Slot 21)
  - Annex
    - General George Washington Commander-in-Chief framed (for Wortham collection) (Bin Slot 22)
    - Robert Curl color portrait 5-10-1997 (Bin Slot 23)
    - empty (Bin Slot 24)
    - Dirk West owls football poster (Bin Slot 25)
    - Shadow box of tools with placards (for Cohen collection) (Bin Slot 26)
    - Hammond Hall color architectural rendering 9-1994 (Bin Slot 27)
    - empty (Bin Slot 28-31)
    - George Rupp inauguration photo framed 10-25-1985 (Bin Slot 32)
    - Malcolm Gillis inauguration photo framed 10-13-1993 (Bin Slot 33)
    - Norman Hackerman inauguration photo framed 9-24-1971 (Bin Slot 34)
    - Kenneth Pitzer inauguration photo framed 10-11/12-1962 (Bin Slot 35)
    - William Houston inauguration photo framed 4-10-1949 (Bin Slot 36)
    - Formal opening invitation framed 10-10-12-1912 (Bin Slot 37)
    - Commencement 5-9-1998 montage of WWII era graduates (Bin Slot 38)
    - Nobel Prize ceremony 12-10-1996 (Bin Slot 39)
    - Ann Holmes oil portrait by Agnes Muench for MFA 1948 exhibit (Bin Slot 40)
    - Asa Chandler oil portrait (Bin Slot 41)
    - Rice stadium photo by Kenneth Goodner 1950 (Bin Slot 42)
- Series IV: Furniture
  - Oak owl student chairs for East Hall Commons (now Baker College) (Oversize WRC 160, Annex)
  - Oak high backed carved chairs with red leather seats from Pres. Lovett's office in Administration bldg. (Lovett Hall) (Oversize WRC 160, 162, Chapel)
    blue leather seats in Chapel
  - Oak coat racks (Oversize WRC 161)
  - Oak student desk chair (Oversize WRC 162)
  - Oak laboratory stool (Oversize Annex)
  - Oak laboratory equipment bookcase (Oversize Annex, Sims Alley)
  - Oak office bookcase (Oversize Annex)
  - Oak library card catalog original to Rice library in Administration bldg. (Oversize WRC 160)
  - Metal land deed filing cabinets (4) (Oversize Annex)
  - Black Windsor chair: William Ward Watkin Endowed Chair in Architecture, May 1999 (Oversize WRC 160C)
  - Small rocket & base (Oversize Annex)